<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An heauenly acte concernynge how man shal lyue made by our suffraine lorde God the father, God the sonne, and God the holye goost, and al the whole clergie in heuen consenting to the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1547</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 95</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844517</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844517</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9337</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23060)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9337)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 21:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An heauenly acte concernynge how man shal lyue made by our suffraine lorde God the father, God the sonne, and God the holye goost, and al the whole clergie in heuen consenting to the same.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Be [sic] Jan Peterson [i.e. N. Hill],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Printed at Amstredam [sic] [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1547?]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in London (STC). Suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-b (b8 blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ten commandments --  Paraphrases, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian ethics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ An heauenly acte concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge how man ſhal lyue, made by our ſuffraine lorde God the father, God the ſonne, and God the holye gooſt, and al the whole cler<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie in heuen conſenting to the ſame.</p>
            <q>
               <p>¶ Make no taryeng to turne vnto the Lorde, and put not of from daye to daye: for ſodenly ſhal his wrathe come, and in time of vengeaunce he ſhal deſtroye the.</p>
               <bibl>Eccleſi. vi.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:3"/>
            <head>God the father.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as we ꝑceiued that after we had created ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſettinge him in a place of high pleaſure, leui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him in the councell of his owne handes to choſe whether that he wolde die or not die. And thus beynge a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual body, after our own ſimilitude coulde not for all this ſtande in the ſame ſtate but abuſinge our celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all giftes, and fel from our precept, neglecting what liberte to him was deliuered, ſo chaunginge him ſelfe from heuenli libertie vnto eternall bondage, in whome we ſe what he was of him ſelfe nothinge but ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, refuſing our liberties &amp; fill vnto the fulnes of his owne ſinne. Whom we lamented of oure mere mercy, cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celling with our ſelfe we wolde not haue him whole loſt, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which conſideracion we exiled him
<pb facs="tcp:9337:4"/> our compani, and to liue in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our waſt grounde, takinge him &amp; his as aliantes &amp; ſtraungers vnto vs, exempt from eternal wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſo brought to worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licies. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding as we haue ſaid our petie and clemencie proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded al maner of thinges and como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites for him by the which he might ꝑceiue our potencial power, as wel before towarde him as then. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vpon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideracion of our owne good will we enacted by oure owne councel ſo to prouide &amp; to ſet againe at libertie, the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers alſo to take away that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was fallen in, which coulde not be done but thorow him that was clene &amp; pure without ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, for ſinne coulde not take awaye ſinne? but the time we reſerued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our owne ſelfe, and at the length to ſtabliſhe and confirme our ſaide act and purpoſe we ſent downe our only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonne to ꝓclaime oure
<pb facs="tcp:9337:4"/> wil what it was, vnto the which he ſet to his ſeales hanginge vpon the croſſe, giuinge vp his life thorowe moſte painful death, by the whiche the attonement was made betwene man and vs, and ſo our anger was pacified and we haue alſo prepared eternal reſt for ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo that after this he wil kepe couenant with vs, and liue in our lawes and ſtatutes that we haue ſet forth by our high court of parliament, both of lordes ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and temporal to the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentinge.</p>
            <p>¶ We haue enacted in our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly court that man ſhall loue vs aboue al thinge with hert, ſoule, &amp; minde, and al the powers he hath, &amp; to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue none other God or goddes but vs, and vs onely to ſerue vpon the paine of euerlaſtinge dampnacion. ¶ We haue enacted alſo by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorite aforeſaid that our bleſſed na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me be not taken in vaine but moſte
<pb facs="tcp:9337:5"/> reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly to be had in honor vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paine before reherſed, &amp; vterly of vs forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wherof our vicegere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Ieſus Chriſt willeth ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſwere at al, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his othe ſhalbe yea, yea, nay, nay, for what ſoeuer is more is ſin. Alſo Iames the apoſtle archbiſhop of al Galacia ſayth. Let your yea be yea &amp; your nay be nay, &amp; Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to whom we gaue great wiſedo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many regions wondred ther at, giueth warni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to great ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rers &amp; ſayth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our plage ſhal not de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>part fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of a cuſtomable ſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rer. wherfore who y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in this is vtterly of vs forſaken.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided always yf ye ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quired of your faith of any in aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye are doutful or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens to your pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhalbe required of you by othe, &amp; beſydes to teſtifie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of your neibour ſo much as eq<hi rend="sup">i</hi>te &amp; iuſtice doth req<hi rend="sup">i</hi>re ye maye lawfully take vs to witnes for your
<pb facs="tcp:9337:5"/> faith, &amp; to take vs to witnes for yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; to iuſtify your neibour in a right cauſe ye may reherſe our na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me for ſo is it not in vaine the acte before notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>Furthermore we wilbe worſhipped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vii. day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal giue vs honor &amp; worſhip for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beneficial kindnes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue done to him, ſeaſing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al labours that daye both he &amp; al his. ¶ Prouided always wher as nede ſhal req<hi rend="sup">i</hi>re as our only ſonne &amp; vice<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerent Ieſus Chriſt gaue exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in healing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſabboth day: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> al actes may redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto our glory lawfully to be vſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> acte before notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Further be it enacted for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vnite &amp; concorde which we wold ſhuld be betwene our creatures, we will one ſhal do vnto another as he wold be don to. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſaid act our only ſon &amp; vicegere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaieth, man ſhall praye vnto vs for the
<pb facs="tcp:9337:6"/> forgiuenes of his ſinnes, none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then he doth forgiue other Alſo the ſaid Ieſus Chriſt ſaieth: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peninge this acte very plainly. Yf ye ſhal forgiue thoſe that hath offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded you your heuenly father ſhal al ſo remit you your offences he wil al ſo that man ſhal forgiue his mortal enemies, and to bleſſe where as they do curſe. And although the auctori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of this acte be ſufficient as is be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore ſpoken yet ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de our lordes of our ꝑliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their voice vnto it. And firſt the lord ſecretary Ihon the euangeliſt ſette his hande and writ: Deus caritas eſt. God is charite, who that abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in charite abideth in God and God in him. And Paule, the lorde chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer ſayeth: Yf he could ſpeak with tonges of men or with tonges of angels ſo that he coulde remoue mountaines with his faith. Yf he ſhulde giue his body to be burned
<pb facs="tcp:9337:6"/> without he haue charite it ꝓfiteth nothinge, ſo that in concluſion he doth affirme and ſaieth. Caritas no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> querit que ſua ſunt. Charite ſeketh not only his owne but that that lon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geth to Ieſus Chriſt our only ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and Vicegerent, whoſe example we wil ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal folow, ſayeng: Manda<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum nouum do vobis, vt diligatis inuicem ſicut dilexi vos. To you I giue a new co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, that ye loue one another euen as I haue lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued you. Alſo ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal vnderſtande, our loue was vnſpeakable towarde him as our lord ſecretary Iohn the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt writ. Sic deus dilexit mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dum, vt vnigenitum ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> daret pro mundum. We had ſuche loue vnto man, that we gaue our welbeloued ſonne for him, that al that beleue in him ſhuld not periſhe, but haue lyfe euerlaſtinge. Wherfore we will by our heuenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that this acte do extende to all creatures one
<pb facs="tcp:9337:7"/> to loue another, for as our lord cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celer Paul ſaith loue is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fulfilling of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary where loue is not there is not god, &amp; where god is not there is wickednes, and where wickednes is there is dampnacion. ¶ Alſo it is enacted ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto his father &amp; mother in do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; in ſo doing we made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ꝓmiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his life ſhuld be longe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> erth to this we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges &amp; rulers to gouerne the erthe to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we will haue dewe honor geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for we haue ſet them as oure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners vnder vs to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute our will for the whiche we will they be had in reuerens, for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boratinge of the ſame, our only ſon obeyd them, &amp; alſo gaue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tribute, tol, &amp; cuſtome ſhulde be giuen vnto them. Alſo lord chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celer Paul ſayth, let euery ſoule ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit them ſelues vnto the higher po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wers &amp; not to obey the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only for fere
<pb facs="tcp:9337:7"/> but for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake. Moreouer Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore fiſher &amp; toke fyſhe dayly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his nettes we exalted him to be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> domeſtical houſholde w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our only ſonne &amp; vicegerent, &amp; ſo boldned his hert &amp; ſprete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we made him to take me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al net whoſe faith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſon of vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing god, to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip agreed, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſo made by faith he was tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated to an high office there made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuꝑuiſer of our church ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>al, whoſe auctorite is no leſſe toward vs then the lord ſecretary Ihon or the lorde cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer Paule to be beleued. And this act doth Peter ſuꝑuiſer of our buildinge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme, ſayenge: ſubmit yo<hi rend="sup">r</hi> ſelues to al maner of ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſake whether it be vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynge as vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chefe heed, or vnto rulers, as vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are ſent of him for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of euell doers, but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praiſe of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do
<pb facs="tcp:9337:8"/> well, for ſo is the will of God here ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> muſt obey them for our ſake, for ſo willeth Peter ther helpe &amp; ſocour with bodye and goodes to be at the kinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement, therfore we wil and by the conſent of our lordes ſpiritual and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, that this acte doth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in ful ſtrength &amp; vertue. ¶ Prouided alwaies ſo that yf fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or mother commaunde any thinge contrarie vnto oure wil, or more then they haue in our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that then it ſhalbe leful for man to ſaye as Peter ſuperuiſer anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the rulers, what time they wold haue put him to ſcilence in confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge and preachinge Ieſus Chriſt &amp; that they had caſt aſyde the ſtone as Peter layed vnto their charge, which was become the head corner ſtone and that ther was no helth in none other, nor no name wherin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſaluacion ſhuld conſiſt but only our only ſonne and Vicegerent Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu
<pb facs="tcp:9337:8"/> Chriſt, boldlye he ſaid howe that he was more bounde to obey God then ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo wol we haue you to ſay, the acte before notwithſtandinge. ¶ Further it is enacted, thou ſhalt not kil. Thou ſhalt not ſtele. Thou ſhalt beare no falſe wytnes againſt thy neighbour. Thou ſhalt not luſt after thy neighbours wyfe. Thou ſhalt not luſt after thy neighbours houſe, lande, ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, maide, oxe, aſſe, or what ſo euer he hath, to this acte al lordes in heuen both ſpirituall &amp; temporall doth confirme and agre vnto the ſame, and vnto the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſours ther longeth da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnacion. ¶ Alſo we enacted, Curſed is he that maketh any caruen ydol or y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, whiche we abhorre, (for it is the owrke of mans handes) and cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed is the handes that maketh them to the intent to haue them worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, for we wil no worſhippe ſhalbe giuen vnto them. For we are God
<pb facs="tcp:9337:9"/> al alone &amp; al honor lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth vnto vs, who was honored whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we were all alone in our own glory, who is wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy to haue honor, but he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> made al thinge honorable. Therfore as our lorde cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celer Paule ſayth, Soli deo honor et gloria. Honour glory w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al praiſe be vnto vs. It reioiſeth vs to heare ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a faythful hert. Tu ſolus dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, tu ſolus ſanctꝰ, tu ſolus altiſſimꝰ. Alſo we knowe that they praiſe vs &amp; laude vs, when they ſay or ſinge w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a faithful herte. Lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mꝰ te, vn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dicimꝰ, te, adoramꝰ te. The do we laude, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do we bliſſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do we worſhip, &amp; the do we glorify. Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as agimꝰ tibi ꝓpt magna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gliam tua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Vnto the giue we tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes for thyne owne great glorye, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no creature hath any glory to glory in but we, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which glory ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be expreſſed with tonges nor yet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hert, yet we be not ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge therof, but in our houſe ther is many ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s prepared for our lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uing ſubiectes, as chriſt hath decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,
<pb facs="tcp:9337:9"/> &amp; yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> courſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory worlde ſhall haue his ende &amp; al thinge co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded as we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue decreed what ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any of our crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſay, how they dyd attaine to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ineſtimable ioyes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhall haue of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues? no no. Could they bye it by any man<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wayes, &amp; to ſay we had no nede of no helpe but of oure owne power cam we hether? no no, they muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ambaſſitor Dauid. No<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nobis, ſed noi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e tuo da glia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Not of vs lord, no not of vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we poſſeſſed theſe ioyes, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory muſt redou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. as chriſt ſaith, ther is none good but god, ſo wil we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal knowe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vs they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothing: for we herd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Iſrael ſayd to Moſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tſtey wold ꝑforme &amp; do al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. Neuertheles to bringe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from their owne truſte &amp; holines, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they myght knowe &amp; ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> worketh all in all thinges: we axed Moſes who ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:9337:10"/> giue them ſuch a hert. Therfore we wil haue al honour we wilbe praied vnto, we will be truſted vnto, for ther is none to matche with vs, for they are oure creatures and we are their God, ſo is there no gods that hath ani ſuch vertues or graces but onely we. Wherfore we ſtreytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde by the vertue of this oure ſayd acte that no perſon or perſons do not take any part or parts of our honour from vs, and to giue vnto ydolles or ymage, but to gyue vnto euery creature his honour, as we haue it enacted, vppon the paine of our euerlaſtinge puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; dred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ¶ Furthermore we haue enacted by our owne power, and alſo by the conſent of our lordes ſpiritual and temporal, that no man dothe eyther adde or take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our heuenly lawes otherwiſe then we haue enacted as we our ſelfe haue ſaid vnto Moſes
<pb facs="tcp:9337:10"/> the ſpeaker of our ꝑliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t what ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me he receiuid our actes deliuering thoſe ſame vnto the childern of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell. Alſo our vicegerent Ieſus Chriſte ſaieth that man ſhal do the father of heuins wil for I come not ſaieth he to do mine owne will, but his will that hath ſent me. Alſo Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt our ſecretary ſaith: Curſed is he that ſhall adde any thinge vnto that that is written in the miſtery of this lawe, yf any man ſhal adde any thing, God ſhal adde vnto him the plages that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the ſame. Moreouer the ſaid lorde ſecretarye ſayeth, yf any man come vnto you and bringe not this doctrine, receiue him not into your houſes, neither ſalute him, for he that ſaluteth him is partaker of his euel dedes. Furthermore Paule lorde chaunceler ſayeth. Other fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacion canne no man laye, then that which is laid alredy. The lorde cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celer
<pb facs="tcp:9337:11"/> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmith it more &amp; ſayth yf an a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gel ſhuld come fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to declare any other doctrine, he forfendeth to giue no credens, wherfore we wyll that our lawes doth ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in his ful ſtrength &amp; vertue without corrupci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of other doctrine.</p>
            <p>¶ Further be it enacted it ſhalbe lawful for al men to haue theſe our lawes ordinances and ſtatutes day lye red in their houſes, as oure cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of oure armies had both Io<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſue and alſo Eſdras, and alſo oure ſpeaker of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Moſes ſayd. Audi filii Iſrael, declaring to them they ſhulde writ it vpon the poſtes and gates of their houſes, and to haue it in remembrance it ſhulde be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vnto their handes and ſo whetted vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that none other doctrine ſhuld take place that according as Paule lorde chanceler ſayeth. He wold of one to go before another in ſpiritual knowlege. And
<pb facs="tcp:9337:11"/> Dauid the noble kynge and one of oure chefe ambaſſitours y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> brought meſſage of oure godlye pleaſure to come, ſettynge forth alſo what profi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tablenes was in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> knowlege of our lawe ſayd. Lex dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i immaculata con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uertens ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>as teſtimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i fideli ſapientiam preſtans paruulos. The lawe of the lorde is parfyte, refreſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynge the ſoule, the teſtimony of the lorde is faithful miniſtringe wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome vnto the vnlerned, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dementes of the Lord are ryght ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge glad the herte, tho thinges whyche God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth are plaine and pure? and they lyghte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the eyes. The feare of the Lorde is pure and holye abydynge for euer, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Lorde are trewe and ryghte in euerye parte more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyer to be deſyred then golde and precious ſtones, ſwetter then the honye combe when it droppeth.</p>
            <p>Thys ambaſſitour kynge Dauid
<pb facs="tcp:9337:12"/> was in aſſurauns he neuer fel after he had our holye and heuenly lawe in his hert where as he ſaid. Lucer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na pedibus meis, verbum tuum do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mine, et lumen ſemitis meis.</p>
            <p>O Lord thy worde is a lanterne vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to my fete, and alſo a light vnto my pathes. And more ouer he ſaid. Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raui et ſtatui cuſtodiri iudicia iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie tue. I haue ſworne euen in the botome of my hert and ſhal ꝑforme it to kepe thy iuſte pleaſures. So that in euery place this faithful Da<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uid profeſſed our lawe to be of won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders efficacy ſtrengthe and vertue, that in maner he dyd wonder at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with a great vehemency ſpake. Mirabilia tua domine &amp;c. Merue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous are thy teſtimonies, wherfore my ſoule obſerueth them, to come but to the dore of thy ſcripture ligh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teneth and giueth vnderſtandynge to the vnlearned. This was he of whome we ſayde we haue choſen a
<pb facs="tcp:9337:12"/> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen to our owne hert. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more our ſecretary Iohn the euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt at the entringe firſt into hys office ſayd. In the beginninge was the worde and the worde was wyth God, &amp; God was the worde, ſo that by his auctorite who ſo euer recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our lawe receiueth vs, and the contrary who ſo receiueth not oure lawe, receiueth not vs. Wherfore man ſhal vnderſtande, it is our wil &amp; godly pleaſure to haue our moſte ſacred worde to go forth whiche is the comforte for man to guyde hys whole lyfe with all, and it was full auctoriſed by our only ſonne &amp; Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cegerent Ieſus Chriſte whiche dyd performe the conſummacion of our ſayd lawe, but we wil by the vertue of this ſaid acte, that any perſon or ꝑſons do not onely receiue this our law carnally but we wil it ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued ſpiritually, or els as Peter the maiſter of our buildinges ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:9337:13"/> it ſhulde be better yf they had neuer aknowen it.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alwayes that yf any perſon or perſons do not acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſhe and fulfyl this our ſayd lawe, that then it ſhalbe leful for hym or them to ſaye with our faithfull ambaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour Dauid peccaui or peccauimus cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patribꝰ nr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>is. Iniuſte egimꝰ iniq<hi rend="sup">i</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatem fecimus. I haue ſinned or we haue ſinned with our fathers we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue lyued &amp; walked ſinfully, &amp; haue done iniquite, ſo that yf we ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue amendement of lyfe be had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge men that then we wyll euen fatherly accepte their hertes for the ſayd confeſſions ſake &amp; ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>all myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the act before notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dinge. ¶ Further be it enacted that euery perſon or perſons which murmure or groge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this our ſayd lawe ſhuld proſecute for mannes conſolacion, we abiecte clene our heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly regime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to euerlaſting punyſhment, &amp; euery
<pb facs="tcp:9337:13"/> perſon or perſons that be tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours of oure ſayd lawes, and be in minde to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue ſtyl in ſuch rebelli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous life, ſhal haue like puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; be wiped clene out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boke of lyfe. ¶ Prouided alwayes we wold ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld knowe our pardon is inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſo that men wilbe obedient &amp; reconſiled vnto our lawe, when ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our grace is offerde. For we wil not the death of no ſynner, yf he wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert &amp; turne, we wil turne to hym againe &amp; wyl thinke nomore on his diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, his ſinnes ſhal paſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſyght as corrupt water that is put into a faire running ryuer. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we wyl ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall lay ful holde tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng hole to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſtitucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue by our owne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; vicegerent ꝓui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> painful paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne dyd ſuffer in whoſe blode we be moued to mercy, when ſo euer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by fayth layeth the ſame before vs. Clerelye as we ſayde before (of
<pb facs="tcp:9337:14"/> the ſynnes that man hathe done) to thinke no more on them, that act be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore notwithſtandinge.</p>
            <p>¶ Further be it enacted our Beati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude ſhalbe vpon almen, that ſhall with a willynge herte do or conſent to obſerue and do all that we haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, their catel, their corne, with al other their ſubſtance, ſhalbe multiplied and encreaſed. And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary euery perſon or perſons that with a grudgynge hert do not or at the leaſt conſent vnto al that we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to the vttermooſt of their powers, that then let them be ſure that oure moſte godly encreaſe ſhalbe withdrawen from them, for curſed ſhal they be, their corne, their catel, with al other their ſubſtance. ¶ Prouided alwayes, it ſhalbe mete for vs to take oure pleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al other. And where as we dyd permyt ſathan to tempt oure onelye ſonne and Vicegerent Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:9337:14"/> And alſo in lyke caſe oure faythfull ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iob, to be tried by aduerſite. It ſhalbe vnderſtande many times we be ſo minded to proue our faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, &amp; to withdrawe vaine thinges fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them to bring them to the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of more parfiter gyftes. For it is our nature diuers times to ſet vp and after to pul downe many times we exalt the wicked to drowne them hole in their lubricite. For of al crea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, we know the intent of the cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we are as the potter that maye do what him lyſt with the lumpe of claye when he hath it in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, to make it a veſſell of honoure or a veſſel of diſhonour, and yet we wyll not be reſoned with al for the cauſe, but we wyl man ſhal aplye his hole wil vnto our will, and to ſaye wyth our only ſonne and Vicegerent Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. Fiat voluntas tua. Not our wylles, but this thy wyll in all thinges maye be done. For thy wyll
<pb facs="tcp:9337:15"/> is holy and is a wyll that can not al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and chaunge, vnto the which all creatures in heauen, earth, and hell muſte obeye. Yf man ſhall thus obe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dientlye proſtrate his whole herte vnto oure correction. Whether it be in loſſe of goodes ſycknes or any other aduerſities, what ſo euer it ſhall pleaſe vs to touche man with all. That then man ſhall be ſure we wyll ſo vſe hym at length, he ſhal not be tempted aboue that he is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to beare. And as our lorde chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celer Paule ſayeth. Who ſo euer doth put their truſte in vs ſhall not be confounded. And oure ambaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour kynge Dauid ſayeth. Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti tribulationes iuſtorum, et de om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus hiis liberauit eum dominus. Vnto the iuſte happeneth many tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bulacions, but the lorde deliuereth them from all. Therfore we wyll man ſhalbe faythful in temptacion yea and to gyue vp hys hole lyfe in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:9337:15"/> our handes, and to feare nothing that ſhall come of vs, what ſo euer ſhalbe layed to his charge but to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>member that in all thinge we ſeke his profyte, yea thoughe that we take his temporall lyfe from hym in the whiche we wyll be glorifyed, and glorifie him agayne. For as it is ſayd. Precioſa in conſpectu domi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni, mors ſanctorum eius. That is the death of the faithful is precious in our ſyght we wyl man ſhall take no paines for our pleaſure but that we wyl double recompens agayne. For our only ſonne and vicegerent hath ſayd. Beati qui lugent. Beati qui perſecuntur &amp;c. Bleſſed are they that mourne for they ſhalbe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, bleſſed are they that ſuffer ꝑſecucion for righteouſnes ſake for thers is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of god, bleſſed are you when men ſhall reuile you &amp; perſecute you, &amp; falſly ſaye al ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of euyl ſaynges againſt you for
<pb facs="tcp:9337:16"/> my names ſake. Reioyce &amp; be glad for great is your rewarde in heuen. what may be more ſayd, what thing can we more promiſe, wherfore ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall vnderſtande in all thynges we wyll that man ſhalbe obedient and confirmable vnto our will and godly pleaſure, the acte before not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandynge.</p>
            <p>¶ Alſo we haue enacted that euery perſon or perſons ſhal vnderſtande that neuer after this we ſhall alter or chaunge any parte or partes of that we haue inacted but as our Vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cegerent ſayeth. Heuen &amp; earth ſhal alter, but our worde ſhall not alter, for our word is our owne ſelfe, and we are not chaungeable in our ſelfe we are omnipote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out beginning w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out endinge, holieſt of al holieſt, ſo fixed &amp; knet in euerlaſtinge truth that al that we haue ſaid can not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor be vndone, but euermore to ſtande. Wherfore by vertue of this
<pb facs="tcp:9337:16"/> ſaid acte we wyl that none other of oure terreſtriall creatures ſhall in their counſel or councelles, inueye or ſuppreſſe any parte or partes of that that we haue ſayde or enacted, but that euery perſon or perſons in al their councels ſhal haue proſpect to our lawes groundynge them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues on our fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion that we haue layed. For we knowe our ſelfe to be as wyſe as they in al thinges, what was mete and what was vnmete, whoſe lawes alſo be ſanctifyed by our lawes if they be conſonant, and whoſe lawes alſo be acurſed by our lawes, yf they be contrarye, ſo that with what meaſure ſo euer is dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, the ſame ſhalbe delyuered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne yet by our law, althinge ſhal be iuſtly iuged.</p>
            <p>¶ Be it knowen therfore that thys is the fyrſte and the laſt parliament that we haue or wyll to enacte oure lawes for euermore. And when the
<pb facs="tcp:9337:17"/> tyme ſhall come (as we haue it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed) to cal kinges &amp; emperours with all other potentates before vs to render accompt before vs for the executinge of oure wyll and lawes whether they haue bene done wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelye or vnworthelye before vs it ſhal appere, and thoſe that we haue founde faythfull and truſty we ſhal deliuer them from the daungers of the lawe to raigne wyth vs euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinge. And againe the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours or malefactours of the ſame, ſhal fal into euerlaſting curſe of the lawe, which is dampnacion for euer more.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Printed at Amſtredam be Ian Peterſon.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9337:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
